A Guide to the Shelton-Winn-Oliver Family Papers, 1764-1872
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Shelton-Winn-Oliver Family Papers, 1764-1872
Library of Virginia
24677, 24827
0.45 cubic feet
Shelton-Winn-Oliver Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 24677 donated by Mary Winn Shelton of Ellerson, Virginia, 3 July 1957. Accession 24827 lent for copying by Mary Winn Shelton of Ellerson, Virginia, 30 July 1958.
Biographical Information
The Sheltons, Olivers, and Winns were prominent families in Hanover County, Virginia. Members of all three families held various offices within the county government. Edwin Shelton (1798-1874) was an officer in the county militia as were Jesse Winn, John Winn, and William R. Winn. Shelton married Sarah Elizabeth Oliver (1810-1887) in 1827.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1764-1872, of the Shelton-Winn-Oliver family of Hanover County, Virginia, consisting of accounts, agreements, bonds, church records, correspondence, deeds, drawings, judicial records, lists, patents, petitions, plats, powers of attorney, promissory notes, receipts, reports, tax receipts, and wills. Collection is divided into three series. Series I: Shelton-Winn-Oliver family papers, 1779-1864, 1872. Series II: Estate Papers of Henry King, 1819-1846. Series III: Shelton-Winn-Oliver family Papers, 1764, 1815-1860.
Papers, 1779-1864, 1872, of the Shelton-Winn-Oliver family of Hanover County, Virginia, consisting of accounts, agreements, bonds, church minutes, correspondence, deeds, election records, judicial records, lists, petitions, plats, powers of attorney, and wills. Of interest are the wills of Isaac Oliver, James Brown, Peter Winston, Peter Foster, John Darracott, and Louisa Thacker; several deeds for property in Hanover County, including papers on sale of property by Mary A. Darracott, widow of John Darracott, and family to Robert Ellett; plats for "Tarkill", "Spring Grove, ""White Chimnies", and "Laurel Meadow;" church minutes, list of members, and records for Chickahominy Baptist Church; election poll from the Negrofoot precinct in Hanover Count for election of a magistrate in 1864; and decrees and other judicial records from the Hanover County courts. Four letters concern the placement of Union artillery on the Shelton homestead 29-30 May 1862, and Union General Winfield Hancock's offer to move the family to a safer location.
Estate papers, 1819-1846, of Henry King (d. 1837) of Richmond, Virginia, consist of the will of Henry King; letters to King regarding sale of slaves; business papers of King; accounts kept by King's administrator Charles P. Goodall; receipts, including tax receipts to the King estate; promissory notes, bonds, and legal papers concerning the King estate.
Papers, 1764, 1815-1860, of the Shelton-Winn-Oliver family containing accounts, commissioner's reports; bonds, deeds, drawings, injunctions, and wills. Of interest are a bond, 29 May 1833, from Henry Clay to Edwin Shelton of Hanover County, estate accounts of Jesse Winn and Parke Street; injunction concerning the purchase of "Darracott's Mill" by Robert Ellett; and a drawing of "Studley" in Hanover County.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Items are arranged chronologically within each series.
Organization
Organized into the following three series. Series I: Shelton-Winn-Oliver family papers, 1779-1864, 1872. Series II: Estate papers of Henry King, 1819-1846. Series III: Shelton-Winn Oliver family papers (Accession 24827), 1764, 1815-1860.
Contents List
- Shelton-Winn-Oliver Family Papers, 1779-1864, 1872 (Folder 1-10)
  - Papers, n.d. (Folder 1)
    - Petition, n.d., John Thacker to the worshipful justices of the County Court of Hanover County. Extensive data regarding the will of Randolph Thacker, who died in 1833., 4 pages
    - Petition, n.d., William H. Lyons, trustee, to William R. Winn, Commissioner of the Circuit Court of Hanover County, to take proof of lost deeds and other instruments of writing. Concerns a deed of trust from Charles Stebbins and Charlotte G. Stebbins, his wife, to William H. Lyons, dated 17 June 1861, for 6 1/2 acres in the town of Ashland, Virginia. Children of said Stebbins are Julia W., Charles, Charlotte C., Harvey B., Wilton P., and Sherley B. Stebbins., 4 pages
    - Deed, n.d., Mary A. Darracott, widow of John Darracott; William P., Richard F., George W., Benjamin F., Susan, Charles R., Ann W., John, and Robert Darracott; William D. and Elizabeth Winston; George J. and Mary P. Herring; all heirs of John Darracott, of Hanover County, to Robert Ellett of Hanover County for Darracott's Mill located on the South Anna River. Deed is incomplete, but includes survey., 5 pages
    - Will, n.d., of Isaac Oliver of Hanover County. Will is incomplete and unsigned., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - List, n.d., of male members of Chickahominy Church, plus part of a sketch of the history of the church., 3 leaves, negative photostats
    - List, n.d., of female members, probably of Chickahominy Church., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Notice, n.d., for Edwin Shelton's school for young ladies in Hanover County., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - List, n.d., possibly of owners and slaves., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - Fragment, n.d., of article on "Rural Plains" in Hanover County, Virginia., 1 leaf, photocopy
  - Papers, 1779-1804 (Folder 2)
    - Deed, 4 March 1779, for 141 acres in Hanover County from James Toler and Mary, his wife, of Goochland County to William Toler of King William County. Recorded in Hanover County, 3 February 1780., 4 pages
    - Deed, 17 February 1784, for land in Hanover County from William Toler and Hanah, his wife, of Hanover County to John Parker of Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 4 March 1784.
    - Deed, 17 April 1800, for half a mill and ten acres on the Chickahominy River in Hanover County from Thomas Norvell of Richmond to Jesse Bowles. Recorded District Court, Richmond, 3 April 1801. Copy., 2 pages
    - Deed, 10 March 1802, for a slave from James Lankford of Hanover County to John Winn of Hanover County. No recordation date shown., 1 leaf
    - Will, 6 August 1804, of James Brown of Hanover County. Proved in Hanover County 26 March 1806., 4 leaves, negative photostats
  - Papers, 1812-1819 (Folder 3)
    - Deed, 17 April 1812, for 500 acres in Hanover County from Thomas Bowles and John Winn to Jesse Winn, all from Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 22 April 1812, 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Deed, 9 March 1812, for 204 1/2 acres in Hanover County from John Austin, Sr., to Isaac Oliver, both of Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 25 March 1812., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Power of attorney, 2 December 1816, from Thomas Winn, Jr., of Woodford County, Kentucky, to Jesse Winn of Hanover County., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Division, 5 March 1819, of the land of Benjamin Oliver among his three sons, David, Benjamin, and Isaac., 1 leaf
  - Papers, 1821-1825 (Folder 4)
    - Chancery suit, 28 February 1821, in Hanover County Court, John Stone and Kitturah, his wife (one of the children of Thomas Cross, deceased); Lucy Cross, widow of Thomas Cross; Nathaniel Cross; John G. Cross; Richard Cross; Mary Cross; Lucy Cross; and Lavenia Cross; infants, v. John Glazebrook, administrator of Thomas Cross, deceased. Division of slaves., 2 pages
    - Plat, [1 August 1821], of the "White Chimnies" and "Laurel Meadow" tracts., 1 leaf
    - Plat, 1 August 1821, of Tarkill Ridge., 1 leaf
    - Deed, 15 August 1823, for 109 of 300 acres in Louisa County, Virginia, from William Brown of Harden County, Kentucky, by Parke Street to Lewis Johnson of Louisa County. Recorded 12 January 1824 in Louisa County., 2 pages
    - Deed, 15 August 1823, for 191 of 300 acres in Louisa County from William Brown by Parke Street to Henry Lawrence of Louisa County. Recorded in Louisa County 12 January 1824, 2 pages
    - Deed, 16 August 1823, for 113 of 200 acres auctioned off in Louisa County from Parke Street, commissioner appointed by Louisa County, and Thomas Witlock. Recorded in Louisa County 12 January 1824., 2 pages
    - Deed, 16 August 1823, for 87 of 200 acres auctioned off in Louisa County from Parke Street, commissioner appointed by Louisa County, and Charles Thompson. Recorded in Louisa County 12 January 1824., 3 pages
    - Deed, 16 August 1823, for 137 1/2 of 222 acres auctioned off in Louisa County from Parke Street, commissioner appointed by Louisa County, and Thomas Witlock. Recorded in Louisa County 12 January 1824., 2 pages
    - Deed, 16 August 1823, for 84 1/2 of 200 [222] acres auctioned off in Louisa County from Parke Street, commissioner appointed by Louisa County, and William W. Beadles. Recorded in Louisa County 12 January 1824., 2 pages
    - Administrator's account, 1794-1824, for the estate of John Street, Jr., in account with Parke Street, administrator. No county specified., 6 pages
    - Notification, 14 November 1824, to members of the Baptist Church of Christ called Chickahominy stating Black Creek Church have had hearing from Hyram, slave of Isaac Oliver, and that he has given full satisfaction., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - Fees, 20 May 1825, owed clerk of court of Hanover County to be collected by Edwin Shelton., 2 pages
    - Deed of trust, 27 July 1825, between John Darracott of the first part, Mary A. Darracott of the second part, and Joseph M. Sheppard, William D. Winston, and Lewis Bukeley, all of Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 27 July 1825., 5 pages
  - Papers, 1826-1829 (Folder 5)
    - Account, 1824-1826, of estate of James Brown., 7 pages
    - Note, 20 July 1827, from Edward B. Crenshaw to the Baptist Church allowing Dinah to join., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - Deed, 1 September 1827, for 1/2 acres in Hanover County being the site of Winn's Church from William Patman and Sally, his wife (formerly Sally Winn, daughter of John Winn), to Anderson Grubbs, James Whitelow, and Francis Blount, all of Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 26 October 1827., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Receipt, 24 September 1827, from Edwin Shelton to Isaac Oliver for money received., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Letter, 20 September 1828, from Reuben Merideth to the Baptist Church allowing his servant Jenny to be baptized., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Decree, 1828, in Truehart vs. Mann., 2 pages
    - Deed of trust, 5 January 1829, for slaves from Richard Barnett to Bowling Starke, both of Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 23 April 1829., 2 pages
    - Copy, 10 January 1829, of patent granted Joseph Cralle on 19 June 1828 for an invention for the grinding of grain., 4 pages
    - Will, 7 February 1829, of Peter Winston of Hanover County, Virginia. proved in Hanover County, 24 June 1829., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Letter, 29 March 1829, from Joseph Winn of Lexington to Jesse Winn of Hanover County containing family news. Also includes letter, 14 November 1826, concerning the account of John Jordan to the guardian of Gail and James., 2 pages
    - Plat, 9 April 1829, of "Spring Grove.", 1 leaf
  - Papers, 1830-1835 (Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 3 July 1830, of a church meeting held at Winn's Meeting House., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Administrator's account, 1831, of the estate of Isaac Oliver in account with Edwin Shelton., 3 leaves, negative photostats
    - Commission, 26 March 1831, from Governor John Floyd to Edwin Shelton appointing him captain in the 74th Regiment, 2nd Brigade, 4th Division., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - Receipt, 2 December 1831, from William Patmon to the Church at Chickahominy for payment., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - Deed, 18 April 1832, for 5 acres in Hanover County from Joseph N. Edmondson and his wife Elizabeth to William Clarke, all of Hanover County. Edmondson had intended to convey the property to John Parker, but now conveys it to Parker's daughter who married William Clarke. Recorded in Hanover County 26 April 1836., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Will, 10 March 1833, of Peter Foster of Hanover County. No probate date shown., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Deed, 3 January 1834, from James B. Clarke to Benjamin Johnson conveying Clarke's interest in the estate of Peter Foster, deceased. No recordation shown., 2 pages
    - Will, 8 August 1835, of John Darracott of Hanover County. Proved in Hanover County 23 May 1837., 3 pages
    - Chancery decree, 21 October 1835, in Hanover Circuit Superior Court, Jesse Winn, administrator of the estate of John Richardson v. Judith Richardson, widow of John Richardson, and et al. Also Thompson W. Pulliam v. Francis W. Scott, late administrator of John Ricardson deceased, and et al. Also includes bonds and other papers related to the case, but which are dated later., 37 pages
    - Deed, October 1835, for 416 acres in Hanover County formerly belonging to John Camm Pollard from William r. Nelson, Robert Carter Page, and Robert Pollard to Edwin Shelton and Thomas Gardner. A rough draft, the deed apparently was never executed., 4 pages
    - Account, 5 December 1835, from Philip B. Winston, clerk of court, to John Nicholas for fees from Nicholas v. Edwin Shelton., 4 leaves, negative photostats
  - Papers, 1836-1839 (Folder 7)
    - Chancery suit, 11 July 1836, in Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery in Henrico County, John D. Brown v. Jesse Winn, administrator of Mosby Sheppard deceased, Overton Mason, and Zachariah Flannagan alias Rice Newman., 2 pages
    - Power of attorney, 25 April 1837, from Hugh Norvell of Barren County, Kentucky, to Jesse Winn of Hanover County. Hugh Norvell and Lipscomb Norvell are brothers of Mary Hendrick, deceased, who was the widow of John D. Hendrick., 2 pages
    - Power of attorney, 2 August 1838, from Martha Bradshaw, widow of Joseph Bradshaw and formerly Martha Mayo, of Montgomery County, Virginia, to Landy L. Mayo of Fluvanna County, Virginia., 3 pages
    - Bond, 21 January 1839, from John M. Sheppard (son of Mosby Sheppard, deceased) and Mary G. C. Sheppard to Jesse Winn., 1 leaf
    - Bond, February 1839, from Ira L. Bowles and Jeremiah S. B. Tinsley as deputies to Charles P. Goodall, sheriff of Hanover County., 2 pages
    - Bond, 26 February 1839, from William T. H. Pollard and others to Charles P. Goodall, sheriff of Hanover County, for Pollard to qualify as a deputy., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Certificate 5 April 1839, for James M. Bagby from John Hope and Pettus W. Chick stating that Bagby never stated he got into the Baptist Church by telling lies., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Articles of agreement, 31 May 1839, between Mary A. Darracott, widow of John Darracott, William D. Winston, William P. Darracott, Richard F. Darracott, George W. Darracott, Susan Darracott, Benjamin F. Darracott, Mary P. Darracott, John Darracott, Ann W. Darracott, Charles H. Darracott, and Robert Darracott of the first part and Robert Ellett of the second part, all of Hanover County., 2 pages
  - Papers, 1840-1849 (Folder 8)
    - Letter, 22 September 1840, from J. M. Bagby of Louisa County to Jesse Winn of Hanover County detailing his schedule for preaching., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Letter, 1 May 1841, from Robert S. Austin of Brownsville, Tennessee, to Charles William Dabney of Hanover County, asking Dabney to bring suit against John Sheppard of Henrico County., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Bond, 8 June 1841, of Robert Ellett concerning his efforts to purchase property from the Darracott family., 1 leaf
    - Deed of trust, 8 June 1841, between Robert Ellett of the first part and William D. and Elizabeth S. Winston, William P., Richard F., George W., Susan, Benjamin F., Mary P., John, Charles H., Ann W., and Robert Darracott of the second part, and Edmund Winston of the third part concerning Ellett's efforts to purchase property from the Darracott family., 3 pages
    - Letter, 26 August 1841, from James W. Strother and Robert S. Austin to Charles William Dabney concerning the estate of Austin Morris., 2 pages
    - Will, 9 October 1841, of Louisa Thacker of Hanover County. No probate date shown., 1 leaf
    - Deed, 1 March 1843, for 370 acres in Hanover County from Frances B. Clarke, widow of William Clarke, and daughter of John Parker and her children, Susan A., Mary R., Sarah E., Richard A., and Fanny B. Clarke to Edwin Shelton. Recorded in Hanover County 15 March 1843., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Bond, 8 March 1843, from Frances B. Clarke, widow of William Clarke, and daughter of John Parker and her children, Susan A. Mary R., Sarah E., Richard A., and Fanny B. Clarke to Edwin Shelton related to their deed of 1 March 1843., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Power of attorney, 8 August 1843, from Robert S. Austin of Haywood County, Tennessee to Charles William Dabney of Hanover County., 2 pages
    - Agreement, January 1844, between Robert Ellett and Mary A. Darracott, William D. Winston, and Darracott's children., 2 pages
    - Power of attorney, 8 April 1845, Mary Cheatwood of Benton County, Alabama, to Anderson Mayo of Chester District, South Carolina. Concerns the estate of John Richardson, deceased, of Hanover County., 2 pages
    - Chancery suit, 13 April 1847, in Hanover Circuit Superior Court, Dudley Richardson, administrator of Betty Matilda Richardson, deceased, widow of Dudley Richardson, deceased, and daughter of John Anderson, deceased v. Francis Page, sheriff of Hanover County and administrator de bonis non of John Anderson, and administrator de bonis non of John B. Anderson, deceased, and George W. Doswell, administrator de bonis non of Jenning Pulliam, deceased., 3 pages
    - Deed, 13 July 1847, for undivided interest in 2 1/2 acres in Hanover County from Tabitha Adams, Joseph Adams, Francis Adams, Mary Adams, and William T. Martin to Edwin Shelton, all of Hanover County. Recorded in Hanover County 28 September 1847., 3 pages
    - Subpoena, 28 September 1847, for the sheriff of Hanover County to bring Robert C. Berkeley, Catharine Berkeley, Charles Thompson, and Nathaniel Thompson to the Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery of Hanover County. Signed by John Hunter., l leaf
    - Notice, 8 November 1847, by Henry Smith for public sale of his land and stock. Includes a note to Edwin Shelton asking him to post the announcement., 2 leaves
    - Deed, 26 February 1848, for interest in 370 acres in Hanover County from Julianne Clarke to Edwin Shelton, both of Hanover County. No recordation date shown., 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Deed of trust, 5 December 1849, for 25, 19 1/2 and 91 1/2 acres in Hanover and Goochland Counties from Alexander M. Peers and Kitturah, his wife, of Goochland County to Charles P. Goodall of Hanover County. Deed to secure debt owed by Peers to W. C. and E. J. Crenshaw. Deed recorded in Goochland County 7 December 1849 and in Hanover County 2[1?] December 1849., 4 pages
  - Papers, 1850-1859 (Folder 9)
    - Deed, [1850], for 45 3/4 acres in Hanover County, part of the estate of John Darracott, from Richard F. Darracott to Robert Ellett, both of Hanover County. Deed is incomplete., 3 pages
    - Executor's accounts, 26 August 1851, of Charles P. Goodall, executor of Parke Street, deceased. Heirs are Mary R. Street, Fanny P. Carver, Parke Street, and Samuel G. Street., 11 pages
    - Deed, 18 October 1851, for 226 acres called "Kimbrough," and also 22 1/4 acres with plat attached from Mary A. Darracott, widow of John Darracott, deceased: William D. Winston and Joseph M. Sheppard, surviving trustees for Mary A. Darracott, William D. Winston and Elizabeth, his wife, William P. Darracott, Richard F. Darracott, George W. Darracott, Susan Darracott, Benjamin F. Darracott, George J. Herring and Mary, his wife, John Darracott, Ann W. Darracott, Charles Darracott, and Robert Darracott to Robert Ellett. Last name is incorrectly spelled Darricott in this deed. No recordation date shown., 4 pages
    - Certificate, October 1851, by Samuel T. Pulliam and Joseph C. Wingfield verifying the names on deed of 18 October 1851., 1 leaf
    - Deed, 14 May 1852, for Darracott's Mill and 2 1/2 acres attached from Mary A. Darracott, widow of John Darracott, deceased; William D. Winston and Joseph M. Sheppard, surviving trustees for Mary A. Darracott, William D. Winston and Elizabeth, his wife, William P. Darracott, Richard F. Darracott, George W. Darracott, Susan Darracott, Benjamin F. Darracott, George J. Herring and Mary, his wife, John Darracott, Ann W. Darracott, Charles Darracott, and Robert Darracott to Robert Ellett. No recordation date shown., 4 pages
    - Chancery suit, 1855, in Hanover County Court, John Thacker v. Jesse Thacker; Martha Thacker; Gatewood Talley and Viny (Malvina), his wife; Richard Rice and Elizabeth, his wife; Lucy Shirley; John Blackwell and Louisa Parke, his wife; Henry Thacker; William M. Mallory; Cassy Thacker; Michaly Thacker; James Thacker; and Ellen Thacker, the last two being infants., 2 pages
    - Division of land, 1856, of Randolph Thacker, deceased. To John Thacker, Mrs. M. Mallory, and the heirs of Nathaniel Thacker., 2 pages
    - Chancery suit, 1856, in Hanover County Court, John Thacker v. Jesse Thacker; Martha Thacker; Gatewood Talley and Viny (Malvina), his wife; Richard Rice and Elizabeth, his wife; Lucy Shirley; John Blackwell and Louisa Parke, his wife; Henry Thacker; William M. Mallory; Cassy Thacker; Michaly Thacker; James Thacker; and Ellen Thacker, the last two being infants., 2 pages
    - Chancery suit, 24 February 1857, in Hanover County Court, James P. Woodson; John A. Glazebrook, assignee of Tarleton C. Woodson; Robert R. Woodson; Mary E. Brittain who was Mary E. Woodson; and Wellington Goddin, trustee for said Mary E. Brittain v. Frederick A. Woodson; William S. Woodson; William Lawrance and Mary E., his wife who was Mary E. Woodson, daughter of John P. Woodson, deceased; Mildred Woodson; William H. Woodson; and Indiana Woodson, the three last the infant children of John P. Woodson, 4 leaves, negative photostats
    - Chancery suit, 2 October 1858, in Hanover Circuit Court, Fleming Terrell, personal representative of Elizabeth Duke, deceased, and others v. William D. Taylor, administrator of Zachariah Burnley, deceased, and others. Concerns John Darracott, Mary A. Darracott, and Robert Ellett, among others., 3 pages
    - Military order, 16 November 1859, from regimental court of inquiry for the 74th Regiment ordering that Major Winn be a committee concerning quartermaster William Wingfield., 1 leaf, negative photostat
  - Papers, 1860-1872 (Folder 10)
    - Chancery suit, 21 March 1860, in Hanover Circuit Court, Flemming Terrell, administrator of Eliza Duke, deceased, and others v. William D. Taylor, administrator of Z. Burnley, deceased, and others. Exhibit in suit, Ellett v. Darracott., 2 pages
    - Resignation, 9 August 1861, of Charles P. Cross to Colonel William R. Winn. Cross resignes as lieutenant of the 74th Regiment., 1 leaf, negative photostat
    - Assessment, 20 September 1862, of damage to the farm of Colonel Edwin Shelton by the Confederate army. Individuals making assessment were Edward P. Meredith, Henry C. Wingfield, and Thomas W. Talley., 2 leaves, negative photostats
    - Assessment, 3 October 1862, of damage to the farm of Colonel Edwin Shelton by the Confederate army. Individuals making assessment were Edward P. Meredith, Thomas W. Talley, William N. Waldrop, and J. F. Satterwhite., 1 leaf, negative photostat